Guide to the Hugh Steers Papers MSS.511
Fales Library and Special Collections
Hugh Steers Papers
1956, 1963, 1982-2004
Fales Library and Special Collections
Steers, Hugh, 1962-1995
Estate of Hugh Steers
MSS.511
4.25 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 media box, and 1 oversize folder
1 videocassette in 1 VHS cassette
4 film loops in 4 35mm film loops
Hugh Auchincloss Steers (1962-1995) was an American painter who committed to representational painting and figuration throughout his career in order to address the impact of Queer identity and the AIDS crisis. The collection contains materials created and accumulated by Steers during his lifetime, and materials generated and managed by his estate after his death from AIDS-related complications in 1995. Materials include personal and business correspondence, notes, slides, transparencies, some personal photographs, resumes and CVs, artist statements, gallery invitations, business cards, price lists, invoices, receipts, lists of donated works, periodicals, press clippings, a pin, some exhibition catalogues, a poster, inventories, appraisals, Steers' official death certificate, a few short film reels from Steers' primary dealer Richard Anderson, and a video recording of Steers' memorial service.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection's name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Burr Steers in June 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.182.
Arrangement
The collection arrived partially arranged by the donor into four distinct series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Gallery Materials
Series III Press Files
Series IV. Alexander Gray Associates/Estate of Hugh Steers Documents
The remaining materials, including slides, transparencies, and prints of the artist's work, were identified as Series V. Reproductions of Artwork.
Biographical Note
Hugh Auchincloss Steers (1962-1995) was an American painter whose artwork has been described as a combination of dreamlike allegory and figurative realism. Steers was born in Washington, D.C. and studied at Yale University, the Parsons School of Art and Design, and the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture. Steers' artistic practice was inspired by notable figures in art history, such as El Greco, Pierre Bonnard, Edgar Degas as well as American artists like Edward Hopper, Jackson Pollock, and Franz Kline whom he believed created artwork that embodies a "gorgeous bleakness" and a "soft glow of brutality." Unlike his contemporaries, Steers committed to representational painting and figuration throughout his career, depicting - through a dramatic and colorful palette - a skewed use of perspective, a skillful depiction of light, and intimate, ambiguous scenes of isolated figures or couples that speak to issues of identify politics, mortality, eroticism, frailty, isolation, defiance, and compassion. Soon after Steers was diagnosed with HIV in 1987, he increasingly focused on AIDS as a subject matter, in particular the impact of queer identity and the AIDS crisis. During the last five years of his life, he introduced a fictive alter ego, a slender figure consistently cloaked in a white hospital gown. Steers passed away of AIDS-related complications in 1995 at the age of 32.
Steers received a Pollock-Krasner Foundation Fellowship grant in 1989, and his work has been exhibited at a number of galleries and museums across the United States and Italy, including the Whitney Museum of American Art, the New Museum of Contemporary Art, the Denver Art Museum, the Albright-Knox Art Gallery, and the Drawing Center in New York City. Steers' work can be found within the permanent collections of the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Walker Art Center, and the Denver Art Museum, and a comprehensive monograph of his work was published by Visual AIDS in 2015.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains materials created by and accumulated by American painter Hugh Auchincloss Steers (1962-1995) during his lifetime, as well as materials generated and managed by the Estate of Hugh Steers after the artist's death of AIDS-related complications on March 1, 1995 in New York City. The collection contains personal and business correspondence, handwritten notes, reproductions of artwork (slides, transparencies, and prints), some personal photographs, resumes and CVs, artist statements, gallery invitations, business cards, price lists, invoices for both advertisements and artwork, shipping receipts, lists of gifted works, periodicals, press clippings, a pin, exhibition catalogues, a poster, inventories, appraisals, Steers' official death certificate, and a video recording on VHS of Steers' memorial service. The collection also includes film reels depicting Steers' artwork that the artist's primary dealer, Richard Anderson, likely used during a presentation about Steers' work on April 13, 1994.
AIDS (Disease); Artists -- United States -- 20th century; Figurative painting -- 20th century; Figurative art -- 20th century; Realism in art; Gay artists -- United States; Estate of Hugh Steers
- I. Correspondence, 1994-2001, undated; 1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence between Hugh Steers, friends, his estate, galleries, museums, and collectors. The correspondence dates from 1994 and 2001 and contains personal and business correspondence. The latter consists of correspondence between Steers and/or his estate and galleries, museums, and collectors.
  - Blank Postcards, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: 1994, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Museums, Galleries, Collectors about Steers, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Correspondence: Cards/Letters Regarding his Works, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Exhibitions and Consignments, circa 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: 1995, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence: Gifts and Donated Works, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: 1996, circa 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: 1997, circa 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: 1998, circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: 1999, circa 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: 2000, circa 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters: Auchincloss, Louis and "Aunt Janet", 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letters: Auchincloss Straight Steers, Nina Gore, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Letter: Cadmus, Paul, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Letter: Franklin D. Israel, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Letters: Gallery Show Invites, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Letters: George, Carl M., circa 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Letters: Hyon MI OH, circa 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Letter: Janowitz, Dorris, circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Letters: John, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Letters: Kennedy Onassis, Jacqueline, circa 1987-1994 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Letters: Love, circa 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Letter: Merrill, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Letters: Ross, circa 1984-1993 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Letters: Steers, Burr, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Letters: Steers, David, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Letters: Steers, Newton, Jr., circa 1985-1992 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Letters: "UNCLM" and Ivan Steers, circa 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Letters: Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Letters: Unsent, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Letters: Whitney, Wheelock; Abbeville Press, circa 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- II. Gallery Materials, 1985-2003, undated; 1.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 media box; 4 film loops in 4 35mm film loops
  This series documents Steers's professional life and work through gallery invitations, business cards, price lists, invoices for both advertisements and artwork, shipping receipts, resumes and CVs, artist statements, and exhibition catalogues. Materials date from 1985 and 2003.
  - Midtown Payson Galleries: Statements of Accounts, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Midtown Galleries: Hugh Steers, "Flaws of Hospitality", circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Community Health Project: Physician Referral List, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Invoices/ Price Lists, circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sales and Consignments, circa 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Invoices/ Price Lists, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hugh Steers: Statements, circa 1993-2002 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Invoices and Consignments, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Price Lists, Sales, Work Lists, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Visual AIDS Film Reels, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Exhibition Related, Etc., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hugh Steers: Personal Statements, Notes, Grant Proposals, Projects, Letter to Editor, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Paid to Hugh's Statement [Price Lists?], circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sales and Consignments, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Invoices/1994, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Inventory and Sales at Midtown Payson Galleries, Inc., circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hugh Steers Invoices 1995, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Lithographs -- Price list, Letter, Etc., circa 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Expenses, circa 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Sales P/A '96/'97 (Hugh Steers), circa 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hugh Steers -- Invoices 1998, 1999, 2000; Correspondence 2000, circa 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Envelopes and Booklets: A-K, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Envelopes and Booklets: L-M, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Envelopes and Booklets: P-R, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Purchasers, Sales, [Adam CU3ENOVIC(?)], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Sales/Inquiries from Collectors: McCall [McSweeney], Simpson, Epstein, and Bertolucci, Straight, and Swandson, circa 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Info Copies [Price list and Gallery Layout for "Hugh Steers: Early Works"], undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hugh Steers Resume/ CV/ Statement, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- III. Press Files, 1988-2005, undated; 2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons
  This series consists of periodicals and press clippings with articles about Steers and his work. Materials date from 1988 to 2005.
  - Magazines: A&U, QW [Gore Vidal], 1992-2005 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Magazines: Body Positive, circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Magazines: Out, Poz, circa 1996-2000 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - M/E/A/N/I/N/G Issue #16, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Press Clippings: Originals, circa 1988-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Press Clippings: Original, 1992-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Press, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Press-related Files and Photographs, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Xerox Press Clippings, circa 1990-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
- IV. Alexander Gray Associates / Estate of Hugh Steers Documents, 1994-2000, undated; 1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton; 1 videocassettes in 1 VHS cassette
  This series consists of materials documenting the end of Steers's life, his funeral, and his estate. Materials include inventories, appraisals, Steers' official death certificate, and a video recording on VHS of Steers' memorial service, and letters sent to Steers while in the hospital. Materials date from 1994 to 2000.
  - Alexander Gray Associates List, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alexander Gray Associates- Steers List; N/Dates List, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Appraisal and Inventory of Estate 1995, 2004, circa 1995, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Condolence Cards/Letters, Hospital Interview, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Estate, circa 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Death Certificate, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Estate Documents 1996/ Correspondence, circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Estate Evaluation, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Inventory of Apartment, HS Project, Xerox Photos, 1 Slide, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Inventories: Estate, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Inventory/Estate, circa 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jay Swanson's Correspondence, Sales, Photos, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jay Swanson: Transparencies 4x5, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Justin Spring, Essay, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Memorial, Memorial Correspondence, Notes, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Memorial Service Transcripts, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Memorial Service: VHS About Steers, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Museum Exhibit Projects, circa 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Projects '96, circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Project 2000, circa 2000 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Sketchbooks, passport, artist statements, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
  - Steers Collectors in VA Database, All Estates and Collections, Inventory, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Xerox and Originals Obituary Clippings, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- V. Reproductions of Artwork, 1983-2000; 1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
  This series contains reproductions of Steers's artwork, in slides, transparencies, and prints. Material in this series dates from 1983 to 2000.
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1987-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hugh Steers: Drawings and Lithographs, 1986-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1989-1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hugh Steers: Sold Works on Canvas, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Hugh Steers: Sold Works on Canvas, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hugh Steers: Biographical, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hugh Steers: Biographical, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hugh Steers: Reproductions of Artwork, 1986-1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hugh Steers: Photographs, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- VI. Jay Swanson/Visual AIDS Materials, 1994; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
  This series contains material collected for the creation of a Visual AIDS database on Steers and his work. Material in the collection dates from 1994.
  - Jay Swanson/Visual AIDS Materials, 1994; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box (Box 5, Folder 9-15)
    This series consists of film reels depicting Steers's artwork that the artist's primary dealer, Richard Anderson, likely used during a presentation about Steers' work on April 13, 1994.